my video on writing ionic formulas with
Dr. Dan. So, this is for introductory
chemistry and we're going to learn about
how to write ionic formulas. So, how do
we go about doing that? So, there's four
simple steps for how to write an ionic
formula for ionic compounds. So, an
ionic compound is whenever you have a
plus and a minus charge that are going
to be bonding together. So, it must be a
metal and a non-metal that are going to
be bonding together. So, that's the
first thing. So when we do that, we have
to first determine what the predictable
charges are of the ions, which is going
to involve using your periodic table and
any reference sheets that you might have
for polyatomic ions. Um, you're then
going to be writing the symbols of each
of those different species. You're going
to write them side by side. Uh, you're
always going to write that metal first.
Don't forget to do that. And then we're
going to go through and learn about the
swap drop method which is a really easy
way of how to get these charges to show
correctly and to be balanced properly.
Sometimes we're going to have to reduce
the subscripts that we're going to show
when we are writing this. So let's go
through it and try to understand how we
are going to do this. So I have a
periodic table here for us to reference
to so that when we go through a couple
different examples that it will make a
little bit more sense. Um, so why don't
we start with just a simpler molecule?
So let's say if I have something like
sodium chloride. So sodium chloride,
what that one is. So you know, we all
use that for table salt. We have our
metal and our non-metal. So the way that
we determine is it a metal, right? It
has to be on the left side of this
zigzag that's here, right? So if it's on
the left side of that zigzag, it's a
metal. So we have sodium, which is all
the way over here, right? So I'm trying
to make that a little bit more obvious
for us. So sodium is in the first
column. So all first column elements are
going to be a + one charge. Now when it
comes to over here on the on the other
side of the periodic table, right, we
have our noble gases which are zero and
then -1. So chlorine would have a -1
charge. And let's just fill in all these
other predictable charges too to save
ourselves some time.
So that means that sodium is going to
have a +1 charge. Chlorine is going to
have a minus1 charge. So that is step
one. We also wrote the metal first which
was also our step two. So we kind of did
two things two things at once, right? We
just figure out the predictable charges
and we wrote our metal first. So the
swap drop method is really simple. So if
we think that this one's a plus one
charge, this is a negative one charge.
What we're going to be doing is trading
is essentially writing the using the
charges to determine the subscripts. So
before we do that, let's just review
really quick what the difference between
a subscript is and a superscript. So if
I have some kind of species,
essentially all these different
elemental symbols have two little boxes
next to them. One of them is looks like
an exponent. The other one looks like a
really under number. So in this case
this is shown as a subscript which tells
you how the number of atoms. Okay. And
now for this upper one this tells you
what the superscript tells you the
charge of that species. So if it's a
plus one that's going to be that charge.
If it's negative one it's going to be
that charge there. So it's always going
to give you some of that information
which is really important when we're
trying to figure out all these little
pieces. So, what we're going to be doing
is swapping the numbers, which is going
to create the subscripts for each of
these species. So, we're going to trade
the ones. So, when we do that, we're
going to be rewriting this sodium
chloride as NA
1 chlorine
1. And that would be our chemical
formula. However, when we have ones, we
don't have to write them. we can just
simplify it to just say that this is
NaCl and that would be our first
formula. So why don't we try to do a
couple more together so that way we can
get the feel of it, get some practice in
with this and hopefully it can get you
get the ball rolling on you being able
to successfully write ionic formulas for
everyday use for your chemistry class.
So with this right, let's do another
one. Let's say I have um lithium and
oxygen. So, first thing we got to do is
determine what the predictable charges
are. So, why don't we do that? And as
and we also figure out which one's the
metal, which one's the non-metal. So,
lithium we can see is on the left side
here. So, that's our metal. So, the way
we wrote it was just perfect. It's in
the first column. So, that's that means
that all right. Well, first column
that's going to be a + one. Now, oxygen
is all the way in the sec the second
column over here, which I'm trying to
highlight, but it's not showing up too
well. That one's going to be a negative
two, right? So, we have -2 for oxygen
and a negative or sorry, positive one
for lithium. So, + one, let's write that
another color.
So, plus one for lithium and then -2 for
oxygen. All right. So, next step. What
was it? So, we want to make sure that
the metal is written first, which it is.
Lithium was our metal. Now, we're going
to swap, drop, and reduce if necessary.
Okay. So, let's trade our numbers. So,
the one go turns into the subscript for
oxygen. And now the two turns into the
subscript for lithium. So when we write
that, this new number is now going to be
where we have L I with a two for a
subscript. Notice how we don't write the
charge. No negatives or pluses. It's
just a number. Now, we're also going to
write the oxygen. And that one's going
to have a one next to it. So we don't
have to worry about writing it. So this
is our correct answer for this example.
Let's do another. So for another type of
species, this is um going to be
aluminum. Let's do aluminum
and nitrogen. So how do we figure out
these charges? So this one is these are
both predictable as well. So just kind
of add in a little note for maybe your
chemistry class if you have to determine
if it if it's a type one ionic or type
two ionic, which some courses do require
this. These are all considered to be
type one ionic compounds. That means
that they're predictable. So there is a
set charge that's always the same on the
periodic table regardless of what
situation it's used. It's always the
same charge, which makes it a lot easier
to memorize and to go off of. And it's
going off our columns, which is always
good. Um, which is an easy way. But
however, aluminum is what would aluminum
be?
If we kind of like zoom in on our peri
table, you see that it's like right
here. How do we know that charge? Well,
there's a little simple little method I
remember for three of these metals which
I refer to as the steps. So, we have
silver, zinc, and aluminum. So, aluminum
is in the third column here. So, with
that Roman numeral 3. So, this is going
to have a +3 charge. Well, now if we
walk down the steps to zinc, it's going
to have a plus2 charge. And then silver
is going to have a + one charge. Write
that down on your periodic table for
your class. So that way you have it for
later. It's going to always be that
predictable charge. And it's if you
remember the steps, it will save you on
a lot of problems. You can trust me on
that for later. Especially with my own
experience of chemistry, it definitely
can make a difference. So aluminum is a
plus three. Now let's look for nitrogen.
Nitrogen is over here on this third
column right here. So I'm circling right
now in blue. Let's erase oxygen here cuz
we're not looking at that one now. So
that is going to be a -3 charge. Okay,
let's take a look at this. So we have a
positive3 and a neg -3. Let's swap drop
them. So when we swap drop the chart the
numbers
that's going to be our subscripts. So
now we have aluminum
with a three next to it and a nitrogen
with a three next to it. Now is that the
correct way to look at this? Well, what
we have to do now is we have to this is
a our first situation where we have to
reduce. Meaning that if the subscripts
are divisible or or they can be divided
by a common number, then you reduce it.
So what would be the common number of
this one? Well, they're both three,
right? So we can divide both these
numbers by three, which would
essentially tell you that all right,
well, we have aluminum nitride would be
our actual answer. And why is that?
Well, it has to be all about balancing
your charges. Being that one of these is
+ three, the other one is -3, you have
to have an overall neutral compound. It
has to be has to not have a charge. It
has to be neutral. So in this case,
being that we have a plus three minus 3,
it cancels out to be zero. So that's
something to always kind of keep in the
back of your mind when you are checking
your charges that when you subtract
these two it's going to equal to zero.
That's something that that's going to
help you with for later. Um now what
about if you have let's say what we
refer to as a type two ionic compound.
Well that's telling you that it's not
predictable anymore. That's something
where you have a variable charge. So
variable is always referring to anything
that's generally is a transition metal.
So a lot of the transition metals have
variable charges. So you have to try to
calculate and determine what that charge
is. So for example, if we did the
following one where I have let's pick
lead and oxygen. Well earlier when we
found oxygen, it had a -2 charge. So, we
know what that charge is. However, lead,
we can't find it. So, the reason is if
you look on the periodic table, lead is
right I always kind of get this one lost
right. It's right here on the periodic
table. It's it doesn't have a charge.
It's under like the fourth column. It's
going to be something that's variable.
So, it can either be a plus2 or a plus4
charge for lead. So, we want to try to
figure out which one is it. So when we
are going to be doing this, well we need
to try to figure out what is what could
it possibly be? Well, these can be
presented to you in a couple different
ways. One of them could be that all
right well maybe it already gives you
the compound. So now you need to figure
out all right what was the charge of it
so you can learn how to name it
correctly. Um, another way that it could
be possibly given is maybe we already
give you the charge and we have to go
through the entire reduction method as
well. So let's say for example, I'm
going to give us an example where let's
say we already know the compound. In
this case, it's going to be lead oxide.
So just like this. So we have lead and
then O2. So how do we figure out the
charge of this? Well, like I mentioned
before, we know that oxygen is -2. So,
what is lead? So, we have to do some
simple little math. Remember that the
whole entire ionic compound must be
neutral. So, it has to have a zero
charge. So, this whole thing
does not have a charge. So, we know that
we have one lead molec or one lead atom.
So, we don't know what the charge is.
However, we do know it's going to be
positive because it is a metal. Now,
oxygen, there's two of them, and that
has to do with this subscript here. So,
being that there's two oxygens, and they
each have a -2 charge, we can go through
and do some little mathematics here. So,
we can try to figure out like, all
right, well, what is going to be our
missing charge in this case? Well, when
we do this, we're going to see very
quickly that in order for this to
balance out, we're going to get -4 for
our oxygens.
And then lead is going to just be our
whatever our unknown value is. That's
all set to zero. So, we can now cancel
out four on both sides here.
And what we'll see is that our unknown
charge for lead is going to be pos4. And
that's because it's always neutral. We
need to make sure that we have the same
charge when we're adding them together.
So negatives and positives should
balance out. So our compound for this,
we can label our charges. So being know
we had lead oxide, we can write that.
All right, this is +4 and this was -2.
when we go through the charge. Now,
there's other types of species you might
come across as well, which could be
potentially polyatomic ions. Um, for
polyatomic ions, uh, these are going to
be from a set list of ions. I'm going to
make another video to show how to work
with polyatomic ions. So, keep watching
and subscribe and like the channel to
see more content. And I hope that this
helped you a little bit. Um, so don't
forget to use your rules when you're
doing these ionic compounds. And I hope
to see you again in the future for
future videos. Thank you so much, and I
hope to see you again. Bye all.
[Music]